After this excurse on wholemeal programming,
let us consider a language feature again.
And actually, it's a language feature we have
already been using, and you have also already
been using implicitly in your exercises, without
probably noticing it unless you already know
about it.
It has to do with types as written here.
And we can actually also see the need and
the use for it when we look at lists again.
But anyway, the concept is more general and
we will also see applications and usages outside
the case of lists.
Let's remember that each Haskell list is homogeneous.
That means that we cannot have, in the same
list, elements of different types.
We can have a String as here in the first
example line.
And that means we have a list of characters.
And we can have a list of Integers and then
we have numbers in that list.
But we can't have a list which contains both
a character and an Integer.
It is not only that we don't know what to
write here.
It is simply ill-typed.
So, it is not something that would be accepted
by a Haskell compiler or an interpreter.
It would simply reject this because it cannot
give it either of those two types, nor any
other type.
It is simply not allowed.
That is, in some sense, bad news, so to speak,
depending on how strict one wants typing to
be.
At the same time, we have seen that functions
and operations on lists have been very flexible.
So, for example, we used "reverse" on Strings
and this gave us another list of characters,
namely, the reversed String.
But we also used the very same function 'reverse'
on Integers, and then we got a new Integer
list, etc.
Also, we had concatenation that could be used
on Strings.
It can be used on lists of Integers, etc.
And we have already depended on this flexibility
a lot.
Also, list comprehensions are flexible in
that sense.
So, for example, we have used (and you have
used in the exercises) list comprehensions
both on the level of numbers or pairs of numbers,
but also on the level of Strings and maybe
even pairs of Strings, depending on how you
solved some of the exercises.
So, maybe you go back to some of the exercises
and look at the functions that you have used
on lists and ask yourself:
What kind of list was this actually?
And did it matter?
And in each case, it would have been one of
lists which are homogeneous.
But functions could be used on lists of different
types.
But *in* each list, the values have to have
the same type.
So, somehow, these two aspects must be reconciled:
The rigidity saying that every list must be
homogeneous, which is very strong.
And on the other hand, flexible use of functions:
to be able to use something like concatenation
on different kinds of lists.
So, of course, we want to be able to write
something like this.
We have just seen this.
We want to concatenate lists of characters.
We want to concatenate lists of numbers.
Also for other functions like 'notElem' or
'elem', we want to be able to ask whether
2 (a number) is an element of a list of numbers,
or whether a character is an element of a
list of characters (that is, of a String).
But at the same time, we want to prevent calls
like this.
So, we don't want this.
We want ++ to work on Strings and numbers,
but we don't want it to work on both at the
same time.
Why don't we want this?
Well, if we did this, then even though this
is a homogeneous list, and this is a homogeneous
list, and ++ can be used on both kinds of
lists, then we would end up with a non-homogeneous
list.
If we would really append this, we would get
a list which contains characters 'a' and 'b'
and then numbers 3 and 4.
And that is not something that we want.
That would destroy the strictness of "lists
are always homogeneous".
And similarly, we want to ask whether a number
is in a list of numbers.
We want to ask whether a character is in a
list of characters.
But we don't want to ask whether a character
is in a list of numbers.
And, no, we don't want this to evaluate
to False.
Yes, in many languages, this would be okay,
and the answer would be False ('a' does not
occur in this list [1,2,3]).
We don't want this.
We want this to be statically prevented.
So, this is not even a question it makes sense
asking.
If these are of different types, then 'a'
can't be an element of this list.
Simply because of the types not making sense.
So, we don't want that this, dynamically,
evaluates to False.
We want that this, statically, is rejected
as a not meaningful question.
So, what are the types then of functions like
those just seen?
Actually, suspiciously maybe, none of these
functions have been given types so far, neither
in the lectures, nor in the exercises.
We have steered around this.
If we had, for example, told you what the
type of "reverse" is, then we might have had
to give you two types.
So, maybe: reverse on characters, which when
given a list of characters, gives you a list
of character values again; and maybe a "reverseInteger"
which, given a list of Integers, gives you
a list of Integers.
So, this is the kind of types that you have
seen so far and that occurred in type signatures
in the exercise templates.
And if we had done something for reverse,
giving it as a top-level function, then we
would have had maybe to decide which of the
two to choose, or maybe in one exercise, write
it like this, and in another exercise, write
it like that.
That is clearly not something that is somehow
nicely maintainable in the long run.
That is not how we want to program.
So, what instead?
Well, the point is, we can use variables at
the level of types as well: type variables.
So, the type of "reverse" is neither this nor
this.
The type of "reverse" is this.
And the "a" here is a variable, a type variable.
It uses the same syntax as an ordinary variable,
but now occurs in a type.
What it is saying is: 'reverse' is a function
from lists to lists, where actually the output
list type is the same as the input list type,
because we have the same variable here.
This is not the same as being untyped.
Let's consider the type of ++, the concatenation
operator.
It takes two lists and gives a list.
So, it is flexible in that sense, you can
give it two Strings and get a String.
But it is still impossible to write something
like this.
So, this is not "anything goes".
It doesn't mean: any two lists and I give
you a list.
No, it is saying: Give me two lists of the
same type, and I also give you back a list
of that type.
And in that sense, this will be rejected,
because it is not two lists of the same type.
So, neither "reverse" nor the concatenation
care about the element type, but they still
care about the homogeneity of lists.
So, in this case, for this reason, it is important
that these lists, even though they can be
of arbitrary types, they have to be of the
*same* type.
Otherwise, ++ will not be applicable.
And that is how this is rejected then, even
though ++ works both on Strings and on number
lists.
And actually, we have already seen a lot of
these examples, we simply didn't write down
the types.
So, if you go back to one of the slides where
I introduced some list functions (there was
a library of list functions that we used for
the first few exercises on lists), then most
of the functions that occurred there have
such type variables if you actually write
down their types.
So, for example, the 'head' function is a
function from lists to not lists, but elements.
The 'head' function doesn't give you back
a list.
It gives you back something which occurs in
the list.
That's why we have here: a list of "a"s to
one "a".
Whereas the 'tail' function, for example,
given a list of "a"s gives you a list of "a"s.
Because it takes away just one element and
then still gives you back a list.
Similarly for "last" and "init".
All these functions are polymorphic.
That's what a type variable means: "polymorphic"
is what I have here as the heading.
I didn't yet mention that notion, but this
kind of types are called polymorphic types,
because they can take many forms, basically.
Working with data of different forms, in that
sense "polymorph".
And of course, a function doesn't have to
be polymorphic in *everything*.
For example, the 'length' function doesn't
go from a list of "a"s to "a" like the "head"
function.
It goes from a list of "a"s to Int because
the output is definitely a number.
The 'length' function is polymorphic, it works
on any kind of lists, but it always returns
an integer number.
Likewise, there is a function for checking
whether a list is empty.
And again, this works on any kind of list,
so, a list of "a"s here.
But it returns a Boolean value.
It doesn't return "a" or a list or whatever.
It returns a Boolean value.
So, the type variable is really used for showing
which parts of inputs and outputs are to be
used flexibly.
And this is *not* flexible because the length
must be a number.
This is *not* flexible because the outcome
of such a predicate check should be a Boolean
value.
Okay, and polymorphism can also occur nested.
For example, the 'concat' function: it was for
concatenating (possibly) more than two lists.
So, you give it a list of lists of something,
and it returns a list of those somethings,
because one list level is reduced.
One nesting level of the list is eliminated.
So, from a list of lists, it goes to just
a list.
And what are the entries in those lists in
a list, and in the outcome list?
Something!
But the same on the input and on the output
sides.
In concrete applications of such polymorphic
functions, you don't see the polymorphism
anymore.
So, if you apply, for example, the "head"
function to a String, then of course, it is
not anymore polymorphic.
At this point, if you give it a concrete list
which is a String (so it is a list of characters),
at that point, it's clear that this "a" must
be characters.
And then what is the outcome?
A character, of course.
So, then this instantiation happens, and "a"
becomes a concrete type.
And then also the output type is clear.
It must be Char because this goes from lists
of something to this something.
So, since a String is a list of characters,
the outcome is a character.
As a side note, actually, these types, if
you really look them up in an interpreter
session, for example, they have even more
polymorphic types than you see here.
So, you get something with some additional
type constraints, like "Foldable".
But we ignore this in this lecture.
So, we consider these functions on lists.
And the polymorphism that interests us is
the polymorphism in the list entries, not
the polymorphism over the list structure (replacing
this with some other data structure than lists).
That's not the kind of polymorphism that's
of interest to us.
So, we talk about these type variables, in
this case, the list entries.
But that also applies to other data structures,
later on.
Also on the input side, a function need not
be polymorphic in everything.
Just as the 'length' and 'null' functions
are not polymorphic in the output, also in
the arguments a function could be non-polymorphic,
or maybe in some of its arguments.
So, let's look at some further examples.
This is the infamous and undesirable list
indexing operator.
It takes a list, and it works on any kind
of lists, and it takes a number as an index,
and it returns an element of the original
list.
That's why we have a list of "a"s, an integer
(which must really be an integer, it can't
be a Bool or something strange else), and
the result will be an "a".
Or the 'take' and 'drop' functions.
They, again, take a number (because you must
tell them how much they should take or drop
from the input list), and then you have a
list.
And that list is polymorphic; it doesn't matter
whether we take from a list of Strings, a
list of characters, a list of numbers, or
whatever, it always works.
But the first argument must be a number and
not something strange else.
For example, the 'splitAt' function, which
had to be used in one of the exercises, again
takes a number because you have to tell it
where it should split a list; then you give
it a list.
And what do you get back?
Two lists.
Of course, two lists of exactly the same type
as the input list.
You can't give it a String and get back a
list of characters (a String) and a list of
something else.
If you give it a String, you get back two
Strings.
If you give it a list of numbers, you get
back two lists of numbers, etc.
That is also important, that in the output
you can have several things.
And, for example, in this case they must have
the same type, but flexibly in the input (in
the element type), but the same element type
for both lists.
And then, you can again have the same question:
What if you have several input lists and want
to be flexible in that?
We talked about ++ already, but let's also
talk about the 'zip' function.
So, what about this?
The idea was:
You give it two independent lists, and what
you get back is a list of pairs.
So, what should be the typing of this?
Well, let's see.
Of course, the lists that you give it have
to be homogeneous lists because every list
in Haskell is homogeneous.
However, unlike in the case of the ++ concatenation
operator, they don't have to be the same kind
of lists.
We have actually used this already.
We zipped things like lists of numbers and
lists of characters.
I don't know whether that already occurred
in exercises, but you can do this.
You can take a list of numbers and a String
and get back a list of pairs of numbers and
characters, for example.
How does this work?
Unlike in the case of ++, we do not only want
to allow "ab" ++ "cd" and numbers ++ numbers,
and disallowing any mixed use.
For "zip", we actually want to allow also
all these combinations.
So, zipping two Strings, zipping two lists
of numbers, but also zipping, for example,
a String and a list of numbers.
So, apparently the type must be different
than the type of ++ because for ++ we said:
We give it two lists of same element type,
and it gives back a list of the same kind.
In the case of "zip" it would give back a
list of pairs probably, but let’s focus
on the input side here.
So, the type of "zip" cannot look like this,
because if it did, then by the same argument
that I used before to say that the type of
++ statically rejects something like this,
also this would be rejected.
But there is no need to reject this because
zipping conceptually also works if you give
it two different kinds of lists.
Each list must be homogeneous, but they could
be of different types.
Well, the type should look like this.
So, again, it is using type variables, but
now more than one.
To express that the two input lists need not
be the same kind of lists.
So, if you had "a" and "a" here, this would
mean we don't care what kind of list it is,
but it must be the same list type in the first
and the second argument.
What we are saying here, is:
We don't care what kind of lists we get, we
don't even care whether the first and the
second list have the same type.
So, they must each be a homogeneous list,
but they could be of different element types.
And what is the outcome?
It is a list of pairs.
And in these pairs, always the first component
has the type as coming from the first input
list, and the second component of each pair
has the type coming from the second argument
list to "zip".
The "a" and "b" *can* be the same type, but
they don't *have* to be the same type.
In that sense, we can more flexibly use this
than for example the ++.
This is important: Different type variables
can be, but do not have to be, instantiated
by different types.
So, this added flexibility doesn't prevent
uses like: String and String.
This is still allowed.
But also String and a list of numbers.
Hence, now all of these calls make sense.
If we zip two Strings, then this "a" becomes
Char and this "b" becomes Char, and the outcome
list is a list of pairs of Char and Char.
If you zip two lists of numbers, then this
"a" becomes Int and "b" becomes Int and the
outcome is a list of pairs of integers and
integers.
And finally, if we zip a String and a list
of numbers, then this "a" becomes Char because
this is a list of characters, this "b" becomes
Int, because this is a list of integers.
And what is the outcome list?
It's a list of pairs of "a = Char" and "b
= Int".
That's why this now makes sense, whereas still
a mixed call for the ++ function does not
make sense because there the requirement
was a list of "a" and a list of "a".
So, if you try to use it like this, then the
compiler would have to decide whether this
"a" variable is Char or Int.
It cannot be both at the same time, but it
would have to be both because this is a list
of "a"s being characters and this is a list
of "a"s being integers.
So, the different type variables here prevent
this problem for "zip", but for ++ we definitely
want that both are of the same type.
That's why the "a" occurs twice in the type
of the ++ operator.
Unfortunately, it is not necessarily the case
that type error messages by the compiler are
as clear as the comments here.
Maybe it is not always as directly visible
from the type error messages if you make a
type error: what was expected, and what was
found.
But at least on calls like this, you can work
this out on your own.
With more complex calls, maybe you need some
help or some digging into different expressions
to find out where the compiler wasn't happy.
Of course, you might have seen something like
this before: types like this, which can express
that a function is flexibly used over different
element types of a collection type, for example.
Probably not if you come from an untyped language.
But if you come from a language like Java
or C# or C++, maybe you have seen something
like Generics in Java.
So, this is Java Generics syntax, but similarly
it is available in other languages of that
family.
This T parameter that you would have in a
generic collection method signature corresponds
to the "a", roughly.
So, this is saying something like: For any
T, I have this "reverse" method maybe, or
a static method, which given a list, which
is a list over something of this type T, gives
back a list of something of the same type
T.
And again, the T here is used more than once,
to express that this must always be the same
type.
So, this corresponds very much directly to
the "reverse" annotation here that takes lists
and gives back lists and they have to be of
the same type.
This is not somehow happenstance, that this
also occurs in other languages.
But it's also not the case that Haskell is
somehow modelled along these examples, these
languages.
The opposite is true.
Haskell and similar typed functional languages
had this feature much earlier than all the
object-oriented languages, for example.
And actually, the Java Generics were designed
by a person (Phil Wadler) who had previously
been a designer of Haskell.
So, really the direction is from here to there
and not in the opposite direction.
Also, in these languages like Java, C#, etc.,
they have different design and implementation
decisions surrounding this polymorphism feature,
and I would claim that the original version
that appears in languages like Haskell or
ML is the cleanest and mathematically most
pleasing one.
In the object-oriented languages, certain compromises
have been made, to integrate for example Generics
with other language features, that were not
necessary as compromises in the more pure
setting of functional languages.
One aspect that distinguishes polymorphism
in Haskell and its functional programming
predecessors from those other languages is
type inference.
Not only did polymorphism occur much earlier
in these languages, but they have type inference.
We need not declare the polymorphism.
The compiler will always infer the most general
type automatically if we don't write down
a type.
So, for example, for the 'reverse' function
we don't have to declare that it doesn't care
about what the element type is in a list given
to it.
Actually, from the definition of the function,
the compiler will work this out.
That's different than in Java, for example.
Let's not look at the list functions, even
though for all of them, again, the compiler
would work out the polymorphic types even
if we didn't write them down.
Let's look at some simpler examples.
So, for example, if we write down a function
like this: f (x,y) = x, and we don't say,
are these numbers, are these characters, what
are they?
Then the compiler will infer: Well, this is
the type, that you see here.
So, the compiler will say:
Obviously, this goes from a pair to an element.
And it doesn't really matter what types these
elements of the pair have.
So, it is pairs of "a"s and "b"s, and the
outcome is "a".
Why is it "a"?
Because the function projects to the first
component.
From this the compiler knows and infers that
this is polymorphic, the outcome is of the
same type as the first component of the pair
that is given, and the second component may
be a different type.
It doesn't *have* to be a different type.
But it *may* be a different type.
That's why a different type variable is used
here.
And likewise, for the 'zip' function the compiler
would also figure out automatically that the
two input lists can be of different types,
unlike in the case of the ++ operator.
So, if this is not declared, the compiler
will still work it out.
Maybe a bit surprising if you see it first,
is that in a case like this, the compiler
will actually force that two types must be
the same.
So, if we write a similar function, which
somehow says "if pi>3 then x else y", then
again, the compiler will figure out that x
and y can be anything, so it is going to use
a type variable.
Because if you look at this if-then-else,
nothing is really done with the x and y, so
there is no something that forces them to
be numbers or so.
Clearly, pi is a number, but x and y may be
anything.
And something of type of x or y will come
out of this.
But actually, the compiler in this case forces
the two values to be of the *same* type.
Why is that?
Because the compiler doesn't try to mathematically
prove that pi is something greater than 3.
Of course, in this specific case, that is
very simple.
So, the compiler could somehow evaluate this.
But in general, we could have any mathematical
expression here, and then the typing of if-then-else
is: here must be a condition, and the then-
and else-branches must have the same type.
Since in this case, x or y, one of the two
pair components, is given back, in the then-
and else-branches, so they must be of the
same type.
Otherwise, this wouldn't be statically safe
to know what the outcome type is.
So, in this case, these must be the same.
But the compiler works this out.
So, really, the point here is:
You can write down the function definition,
and the compiler will find out the least restrictive
conditions on the types of the inputs and
outputs so that it always works, and it always
makes sense.
That doesn't mean that you should, from now
on, forget about writing type signatures.
Often it is still useful to write your own
type signatures, be they polymorphic or not.
Simply to express what you expect about your
function, and then the compiler can compare
this, and will compare this, to what the compiler
works out.
And you can write down a more specific type.
So, if you say: I want my f-function to be
from pairs of integers and integers to integers,
then that's fine.
The compiler won't complain about this.
The compiler will complain if you claim more
generality for your functions than they really
provide.
The compiler will not complain if you give
a more specific type than the one that the
compiler would have inferred on its own.
Another pleasing aspect of polymorphism in
a language like Haskell is that this polymorphism
has really interesting semantic consequences.
We can see this, if we recall from earlier
in the lecture the following law, where I
talked about interchanging the order in which
we reverse a list or apply functions to the
elements of the list.
So, you probably remember this law from then.
Maybe surprisingly, or maybe not surprisingly
to you, this holds not just for arbitrary
f and lists.
So, I said we could put any list here.
We can take any function here.
Actually, also the "reverse" can be exchanged
for something else, namely for any function
of the same type.
So, "reverse", we now know, has this type:
list of "a"s to list of "a"s, for whatever
"a" is.
And actually, this law doesn't depend on what
"reverse" is doing, that it is reversing the
list.
We could replace this by any function g which
has the same type as this here, and the law
would still hold, no matter how the g is defined.
And that is, I would say, a bit surprising
at least.
So, you could maybe think about what functions
you can think of that have the same type.
We have actually already seen some.
The 'tail' function and the 'init' function,
for example, have this type.
But also other functions like taking the first
5 elements of a list, for example, also have
this type.
And also other functions that you can think
of.
And whatever of these functions you plug into
the two places of "reverse" here, this law
will hold.
Much more generally than for specific for-loops,
where you could also maybe find a law.
So, this is a law that comes almost for free.
It applies very freely, and depending on just
the type of this function here.
And since I mentioned earlier that laws like
this can be used for program optimization,
this also means that there is a lot of potential
for doing this in a compiler, for example.
Because you can deduce laws from the types
of functions, like in this case.
Let's briefly return to how this was formulated
in the C-like imperative setting.
Actually, the "reverse"-claim I just discussed,
earlier occurred in the context of comparing
these two for-loops, and comparing them to
a Haskell version.
And then this "reverse"-claim came about.
And at that point in the lecture, I already
mentioned that in an imperative setting, these
loops may not be equivalent, depending, for
example, on what the f is doing.
So, there could be a difference here.
And now we know that even if they *are* equivalent
in certain situations, for example because
we know more about the f and about what's
happening, at least they are not as general.
This "reverse"-claim is much more general.
Now that we also know that the 'reverse' function
can be replaced by any function from lists
to lists, polymorphically; that is certainly
not true for this.
So, these two loops might be interchangeable
in certain situations that we can check with
some work, but they do not generalize in the
way that this "reverse"-claim generalizes
to any function of the same type.
For any specific function like "tail", you
could also see, well, what does this means
in the context of for-loops?
Is there a corresponding result in an imperative
setting?
Maybe we can work this out, but we don't get
a general law like in the case earlier.
Also Generics don't give you this.
So, even though Generics in Java, somehow,
correspond to polymorphic types, they don't
give you this kind of results.
This is all nicer in a setting like Haskell.
And that is not just an accident.
It comes from the expression-based character
of the language, where we can talk about laws
between expressions.
It comes from the type discipline.
It comes from the mathematical basis, that
everything is compositionally designed and
defined.
So, in that sense, it is really something
given as a plus on top of the other expressiveness
that we already have.